how to make a blanket correctly And
як правильно робити ковдрію І
I will say that there
я скажу що єдиного єдиного правильного
is no single correct way and I will share my own
способу немає і я Поділюсь власним
experience I will tell you how it happens at
досвідом я розкажу як це відбувається в
Google how it happened in the ticket what
Гуглі як це відбувалося вибілет які
things work which don't work what types of
штуки працюють які не працюють які типи
blankets are there and some aspects of implementation
ковдрів є і якісь аспекти по реалізації
but let's first take the classic version of
але давайте спочатку класичний варіант
the blanket to which we are used to this
ковдрив'ю до якого Ми звикли це
we write the code in a separate branch then
ми пишемо код в окремій гілці потім
create a Pull request merger Quest for a
створюємо Pull request merger Quest на
senior developer who looks at something
старшого розробника який щось дивиться
leaves comments you fix then
залишає коментарі ви виправляєте потім
It all gets merged into the main branch and in
Це все маржиться в головну гілку і в
principle this is a working approach the only thing here is to
принципі це робочий підхід єдине тут
remember a few things first so that
треба Пам'ятати про декілька речей перше
it works
щоб це працювало
what we did in the ticket for example we
те що ми робили вибілет наприклад у нас
had guidelines on how the code should look
були гайдлайни по тому як має виглядати
what practices are correct which we have
код які практики правильні які у нас
standardized very often there are two
стандартизовані дуже часто буває два
approaches correct and it is better to just choose
підходи правильні і краще просто обрати
one so that the code is easy to read by all
один щоб код було легко читати всі
teams all campaigns and so that this code you
команді всі кампанії і щоб цей код ви
can easily I don't know look at an example of
легко могли не знаю подивитися приклад
writing the code and it is easy to read and
написання коду і легко прочитати і
understand it and when you get
зрозуміти його і коли у вас набираються
these practices there are more and more of them  at
ці практики їх все більше і більше в
some point riv uber starts writing
якийсь момент рів юбер починає писати
here put so much I don't know the indents
отут постав стільки-то Не знаю відступів
two
два
of the spaces here in 4 here something else And at some
з пробіли тут в 4 тут ще щось І в якийсь
point
момент
most of the comments are about
велика частина коментарів стосується
style so I think many people
стилю тому я думаю багато хто
used the already opened priter and
використовував вже розкритим прітєр і
yeslint that is use
єслінт тобто використовуйте по максимуму
automation to the maximum as much as possible we would white out
автоматизацію наскільки це можливо ми
words used it with all
вибіли б використовували її слів з усіма
that can be found plugins each
якими можливо знайти плагінами кожен
plugin was configured for our Style
плагін був налаштований під наш Style
Guide and in addition we wrote there is such a
Guide і окрім того ми писали є такі
plugin there is a follow plugin more called
плагін є слід плагін more називається на
npi you can search and we
npi можете пошукати і ми туди по
added rules there little by little
трошечки додавали правила
[music]
[музика]
to cover the problems that we saw during
щоб покрити проблеми які ми бачили під
some interview and here automation
час якого інтерв'ю і ось автоматизацію
so that we don't write every time by hand to
щоб ми не писали кожен раз руками щоб
fix it on so so so so that the developer
виправ це на так от отак щоб розробник
senior developer there did not take part
старший розробник там не приймав участі
in this that is automation to the maximum
в цьому тобто автоматизація по максимуму
but it starts with the fact that you should
але це починається з того що у вас мають
have some standards from the very beginning
бути якісь стандарти з самого початку
standardized approaches the second question
стандартизовані підходи друге питання
that often arises is who should do this
яке часто виникає Це хто має робити це
review senior developer there Signor in the
рев'ю старший розробник там Синьйор в
team that  led or feather and there are different
команді тим лід або пір'ю і є різні
approaches and those that work and it all depends
підходи і ті робочі і це все залежить
on
від
first of all do you have these families of developers
по-перше Чи є у вас ці сім'ї розробників
in the team how loaded they are and
в команді наскільки вони завантажені і
so on from your goals also in Google
так далі від ваших цілей також в Гуглі
for example feathers are practiced i.e. in
наприклад практикується пір'ю тобто в
Google I can create a quest and in
Гуглі я можу створити квест і в
the reviver put any other
ревівером поставити будь-якого іншого
Googler I can be there
гуглера я можу бути там
can a senior for example put John
може сім'їор наприклад поставити Джона
June signor whatever And
Джун сіньора як завгодно І
of course Usually this is put by an engineer from
звісно Зазвичай це ставиться інженер з
your team but we will talk about Google a little
вашої команди але про Google ми трішечки
later i.e. let's
пізніше розповімо тобто давайте ще раз
summarize again the standard approach review
підсумуємо стандартний підхід review
is done
робиться
before pouring into the main branch you need to
перед тим як влити в основну гілку треба
have guidelines
мати гайдлайни
to the maximum automate the maximum
по максимум автоматизувати максимальну
amount of static analysis which only
кількість статичного аналізу який тільки
you can screw in to simply
ви можете прикручувати щоб просто
unload
розвантажити
reviewereve It can be feathers It can be a
reviewereve Може бути пір'ю Може бути
review of the senior senior of some
review старшого старшого якогось
developer or those people or Tim leads and
розробника чи тих людей чи Тім лідам і
tests usually fit tests this is a
тести зазвичай приганяється тести це
standard approach Now let's
стандартний підхід Тепер давайте
go back to Google how this works in
повернемось до Гугла як працює ця в
Google angular is very similar everything is very much
Гуглі вуглі дуже схожа все дуже багато
static  analysis of various aspects is
статичного аналізу різнопланевого
practically there for different types of files,
практично там під різні типи файлів
that is, a huge amount of static
тобто величезна кількість статичного
analysis that has not been done for years, besides,
аналізу який не вироблявся роками крім
it is as if Google white on the whole of
того Він якби Google white на весь
Google, a lot of things are the same and the code
Google багато чого однакового і кодова
base looks holistic there,
база виглядає цілісно там
one project and another are very similar in
один проєкт і інший дуже схожий по
writing, which is very cool because in Google
написанню це дуже круто тому що в Гуглі
you practically do not use
ти практично не користуються
stackoverflow, but you use the
стековертфову а користуєшся пошуком по
code search, you find cool examples and you understand
коду знаходиш класні приклади і розумієш
how to use this or that library,
як той чи інший бібліотеку використати
but let's go back to what is
але давайте повернемось чим
different about the review deck in Google,
відрізняється колоду review в Гуглі
first - it is there with feathers, that is, like me
перше - це там пір'ю тобто як я
on anyone, but in addition to reviewing, because
на кого завгодно але крім того що рів'ю
someone is a loser and puts a bow with Good, you
ведь хтось згублерів і ставить там лук з
also have such a thing as a
ще є така штука як
redubility review, that is, a certain number of
редубіліті рев'ю тобто певна кількість
people have it, that is, in addition to the fact that an engineer
людей мають тобто крім того що інженер
who knows about the leak will tell you that this candle is
який знає про течу вам скаже що це свіча
made correctly, someone else has to say
правильно зроблена ще хтось має сказати
that your code is written in accordance with the
що ваш код написаний відповідно до
guidelines, and besides, with all this,
гайдландів гайдлайнів і при тому при
you understand that before that there was
всьому ви розумієте що до цього було
a lot of static analysis,
дуже багато статичного аналізу
so there are people who have this redubility
тому є люди які мають цей рідибіліті
status, for example on  typescript
статус наприклад на тайбскрипт його
can be obtained there in six months in C++, you
можна отримати там за півроку на c++
can do it there, I don't know, you can probably
можна там я не знаю можна мабуть їй 5
put it for 5 years to get this
років покласти щоб отримати цей статус
readability status and
рідибіліті і
you can't put your code in until someone with the
ти не можеш влити свій код поки хтось зі
status of a year of morons like the corresponding
статусом рік дебілів типу відповідному
step checks it and it's not
степу не поставить галочку і це не
necessarily with your team. For example,
обов'язково з твоєю командою Наприклад
if we have a team, we
якщо ми от в нас є команда Ми там з
switch from one programming language to
одною мову програмування переходимо на
another, there may not be a single
іншу нас може не бути взагалі жодної
person with this readability status at all, and we
людини з цим статусом рідибіліті і ми
will ask someone or an automatic
будемо просити когось чи автоматичну
system will assign someone somewhere from
систему буде когось назначати десь з
Google
Гугла
to check the code for compliance with the
перевірити код на відповідність
guidelines and somehow without practice. This
гайдлайнам і якимось без практикис і Ця
thing works. Because
штука працює Тому що
when you come to a project, you
коли ти приходиш на проект був літ ти
may not know the technological stack, it's
можеш не знати технологічного стеку це
all new to you, and it's also very
все для тебе нове і це крім того дуже
desirable that over time someone in the team
бажано щоб з часом хтось в команді
gets this readability status, but
отримав цей статус люди біліті але
for example, what can I say, I
наприклад що я можу сказати
have a junior developer in my team
в мене в команді є молодша розробник
who has which has readability and can
який має яка має рідибіліті і може мій
review my code from and say wrote and checked it
код за review від і сказать писав і
and this code will be accepted, but
галочку і цей код буде прийнятий але
if  I'm her trump card, I don't have this
якщо я її козир'ю мене нема цього
status among the debilitated and I'll put it so that
статусу серед дебілітій і я поставлю щоб
the code looks cool but I still need
код виглядає класно але ще потрібен буде
someone to put it among the debilitated and
хтось хто поставить серед дебіліті і
that is, my one rivyu is not enough but
тобто мого одного рів'ю недостатньо але
if both videos I asked can be from
якби обидві ролики Я задав можуть бути у
one person
одної людини
this is in terms of Google which is interesting also what in terms of
це в плані Гугла що цікаво ще що в плані
standard Well that's what I never
стандартного Ну то що я так ніколи не
thought about but it works very cool in
задумувався але дуже класно працює в
Google
Гуглі
in general the approach in mental That's when you
взагалі підхід у ментальний От коли ви
create a network quest for someone You
створюєте мережі квест на когось Ви
have to make
маєте максимально максимально полегшити
life as easy as possible for the person who will recruit you
життя тій людині яка буде вас ребруювати
she generally has her own job her own
вона взагалі в неї є своя робота свої
tasks and it is
задачі і
desirable that If you want a high-quality field and
бажано щоб Якщо ви хочете якісно ріллю і
that the person does not strain
щоб людина не напрягалась
and is ready to check you again and
і готова була вас перевірювати ще раз і
it was all fast then
це все було швидко тоді
do everything so that your me quest field was
зробіть все щоб ваш мене квест поле був
simple for rivyu
простим для рів'ю
put in one merch quest things that
помістіть в один мерчиквест речі які
relate to just this feature there
стосуються ось тільки цієї фічі там
this this change here you make some
цього цієї зміни от ви робите якусь
change related to something here you describe
зміну пов'язану з чимось от ви опишіть
it besides that very, very much what I really
її крім того дуже-дуже те що мені дуже
liked Very often in the description to
сподобалось Дуже часто в опис до
Merch Vesta insert a screenshot, that is,
мерчек Веста вставляють скріншот тобто
if you changed something in the code and it
якщо Ви змінили щось в коді і це
changes, it concerns ua, it changes
змінюється це стосується ua це змінює
visually how your interface looks,
візуально як виглядає ваш інтерфейс
take a screenshot, put a link to the
зробіть скріншот помістіть лінку на
screenshot so that the person who reviews or
скріншот щоб людина яка review або
even does a screenshot can do this, too, it is often
навіть скрінка зробіть це теж дуже часто
written as screenshotting. That's how it
пишеться скрінкаство То так воно себе
behaves. A person says they regulate the code, they
веде людина каже регулюють код вона
immediately see that. Here it was like this and here it is,
відразу бачить що Ось вона була так і
besides, they often
ось так крім того не скріншоті часто
sign screenshots here, so it was, so it became like this and
підписують ось тут так було стало так і
it helps a lot
це дуже допомагає
and
і
in general, yes, we could end on
в цілому Да От ми могли б закінчити на
this topic and say, This is how it works and
цій темі і сказати Ось так працює і
maybe I didn't say anything like that. But there is an
можливо нічого такого не сказав Але є
interesting phrase that I
цікава фраза яку я
read, some cool ones, I don't remember the name of the
вичитав якісь класні не пам'ятаю назву
book, but I remembered the phrase and the
книги але фраза мені запам'яталась і
phrase sounds like this. If you just write
фраза звучить так якщо ви просто пишете
code, you accumulate technical debt, that is,
код ви накопичуєте технічний борг тобто
imagine that you just write
Уявіть собі що ви просто пишете
cool ones, for example, you have a code
класно якісь ну наприклад у вас кодова
base that allows you to add new
База яка дозволяє додавати там нові-нові
components there, and you add modules there, you
компоненти і ви додаєте там чи модулів
add module by module, module by
додаєте модуль за модуль модуль за
module, and if you revise this module,
модулем і якщо ревізувати цей модуль
the architecture was cool, everything  cool and
архітектура була класна все класно і
even if these modules review howl Everything is
навіть якщо ці модулі review вити Все
great but initially the system was
супер але спочатку система була
designed and triggered for 10 modules
розрахована і спровокована на 10 модулів
And you, for example, already have
А вас як наприклад вже
300 or even 50 and it already looks like it is
300 чи навіть 50 вже і вона вже виглядає
not working as expected in addition to that it has
як працює не так як очікувалось крім
already been six months and you already
того вже ваш пройшло півроку і ви вже
understand that you did not foresee
розумієте що все ви не передбачили
some things and
якихось речей і
such a thing, the old press does not
таке от пресамітко древ'ю Вам уже не
help you much because you see that
сильно допомагає тому що ви бачите що
the code is written in the same way as the previous one,
код написаний так само як і попередній
everything is cool, each individual comma
все класно кожен окремий коматочок
works great but in fact you have already
працює супер але насправді ви вже
accumulated technical debt and you
накопичили технічного боргу і ви його
accumulate it and accumulate it and accumulate it,
накопичуєте і накопичуєте і накопичуєте
so there is another type of preview, even
тому є ще другий тип прев'ю навіть
several types. Power is written in such a type
декілька типів Пауер пишеться такий тип
that you perform when you simply read the
який ви здійснюєте коли просто читаєте
code, so you read the code you see that something is
код от Ви читаєте код бачите що щось ним
wrong with it and you have to improve it, you have a
не так і маєте його вдосконалити маєте
team reading the code you see that you will
команда читає код бачите Тобто ви будете
simply see that something is wrong but I did
просто бачити що воно щось не так але я
not want to talk about such a
хотів розповісти навіть не про такий
case at all But about
випадок А про
the blanket that was thrown at us, the so-
ковдрію яке от нас було вибілет так
called architectural review, this is a periodic
зване архітектурна рев'ю це періодичний
review once  a month
рів'ю раз в місяць
it happened again every few months
відбувалось ще раз в декілька місяців в
depending on the project and the idea was
залежності від проекту і ідея була така
that we have
що у нас
people writing a project and
люди пишуть проєкт і
there is a team that already has a lot of projects
є команда яка вже багато проектів
interviews the main thing is coming to the project and
інтерв'ю головне приходить на проект і
starting its review from compliance with the
починає його рев'ю від на відповідність
architecture itself for compliance with
саму архітектура на відповідність
some good practices
якимось гарним практикам
and for this we had or crosses for the
і у нас для цього були чи клісти для
front
фронта
with the main mistakes that
з основними помилками які допускають
engineers who write the front make architectural
інженери які пишуть фронт архітектурні
mistakes main mistakes that are made
помилки основні помилки які допускаються
on the backend
на бекенді
Security main mistakes related to
Security основні помилки пов'язані з
security and the architectural review
security і архітектурне рев'ю
took place as follows
відбувалося наступним чином
we had these checklists Which were given to the
у нас були оці чеклісти Які давались
team which were given
команді які давалися
equally and Well they were in euros actually and
рівною і Ну вони були в євро власне і
then the team and the reviewer worked in
потім команда і reviewer працювали
absentia i.e. banal things there could
заочно тобто банальні штуки там могли
be how the work with configs is done
бути як відбувається робота з конфігами
checking for such frequent
перевірка на такі часті
anti-patterns like anemig to the Main Model
антипатрний типу анеміг до Мейн Model
Who doesn't know can read but I
Хто не знає може почитати але я зроблю
think I will make a separate video about
думаю що окреме відео про
but
але
this or crosses that contain this information
цей чи хрести які містять цю інформацію
and the reviewer checks the project separately
і reviewer перевіряється проект окремо
he starts by simply launching the
він починає з того що просто запускає
project
проект
on the native the project should be launched one
по рідній проект має запускатися одною
team and so on then the
командою і так далі потім
team also goes through these security officers
команда теж по цим чекистам проходиться
everything is collected in some document everything that
збирається все в якийсь документ все що
does not match
не відповідає
then this document will be processed after all
потім цей документ буде оброблятися
the plan for action and
все-таки план до дій і
then the team is called that years for
потім вже команда зідзвонюється тим літ
example it starts with drawing a
наприклад починає з того що малюють
diagram of the project containers so that
діаграму контейнерів проекту для того
each developer does not just see
щоб кожен розробник немає просто бачити
that is there I don't know if you have heard of such a thing
тобто є не знаю чи не чули така штука
called all for Model C4 and these are such
називається всі for Model C4 і це такі
architectural diagrams that allow
архітектурні діаграми які дозволяють
very simple very simple approach there in 5
дуже прості дуже простий підхід там за 5
minutes you can learn it allows you
хвилин його можна вивчити дозволяє
to describe the project and there one of the types of
описати проект і там один з типів
diagrams is called a diagram of containers
діаграм називається діаграма контейнерів
when we
коли ми
write we draw that we have
пишемо малюємо що у нас є
User there is a client browser or mobile
User є є клієнт браузер чи мобільний
application there is
application є
Note
Note
numeracy there are some workers there is a
чисб-кенд є там якісь воркер є база
database there is a Store through three that is these
даних є там Store через три тобто оці
main processes that
основні процеси які
create I mean processes if in
створюють маю на увазі процеси якби в
mobile
мобільному
on the server and so on the database process here on
на сервері і так далі процес бази даних
my processes essentially subsystems Which
от на мій процеси по суті підсистеми Які
create our entire
створюють всю нашу
program our entire platform for example and a
програму всю нашу платформу наприклад і
person draws it and then further for two
людина це малює і потім далі вже двох
hours with a bell already in revive after the
годин із дзвон вже у revive після
correspondence level There is a list  questions and goes
заочного рів’ю Є список питань і
through the code we prepare a
проходить проходимося по коду готуємо
document and an action plan and for example in two
документ і план дій і наприклад за два
months something is fixed there in two
місяці там щось виправляється через два
months we do a second review and so
місяці ми робимо повторне рев'ю і так
on And this thing is also quite workable
далі І ця штука теж така досить робоча
because
тому що
as I said that the
як я вже сказав що
preview is often not enough time even at
прив'ю часто недостатньо час навіть в
Google when we launch something there we
Гуглі коли ми там щось запускаємо ми
gather the team and someone who was
збираємося команда і хтось хто
responsible for a big feature tells
відповідав за велику фічура розповідає
how he implemented it shows the code
як він її імплементував показує код
answers the question And this is such a review is
відповідає на питання І це таке review
already reflected when all the code is poured into the
вже відбивається коли весь код влит в
main branch so you
головну гілку тому
don't
не
overestimate someone not even so not
дооцінюєте отакого не навіть так не
overestimate the review that you do for
непереоцінюють рів’ю яке ви робите на
almost a year of quests because this is simply not
майже рік квестах тому що цього просто
enough
недостатньо
so in principle
так в принципі
that's all but if you have any questions and
це все але якщо у вас є якісь питання і
you would like some topic so that I can open the
ви хотіли б якусь тему Щоб я розкрив
depths deeper write in the comments and
глуб глибше пишіть в коментарях ну і
of course put a like subscribe I will
звісно ставте лайк підписка буду
create even more videos
створювати ще більше відео